## Alessio Valentini, Ph.D.

I am a passionate researcher who lives at the interface between computer science and computational chemistry. I built my career delivering high quality software to solve chemistry problems. I am an eager learner who enjoys new challenges and tinkers with all things computer science.

**Work Experience:** 

- Research Associate/PostDoc at Stanford University. Project leader and main developer of the Retropaths package, a new software that automates exploration of chemical synthesis channels using graph theory, funded by a multimillion MURI DOD ONR grant (California 2020-present).
- **PostDoc at University of Liège.** Project leader and main developer of a package to perform and analyze quantum dynamics for attosecond time-scale events (*Belgium 2016-2019*).
- PostDoc at University of Siena. Developed tools in the OpenMolcas quantum chemistry suite for semiclassical dynamics and automatic generation of hybrid quantum mechanics / molecular mechanics protein models (Italy 2015-2016).

**Skills:** 

- Developed several Python (Expert 11 years) and Haskell (Intermediate 3 years) packages for molecular dynamics, reaction discovery, data analysis and data wrangling pipelines.
- Proficiency in developing high performance codes in collaborative settings, as proven by my work in the OpenMolcas suite and in the Martínez group at Stanford University.
- Highly experienced in system administration. Setup and managed two university clusters for scientific calculations (2009-2019).
- Effective communication skills, with a strong passion for visual effects and 3D rendering, as proven by my 8 presentations and 2 awards at international scientific conferences.

### **Career achievements:**

 Published 22 articles with more than 2400 total citations in peer-reviewed journals in the fields of photochemistry, photobiology, reaction discovery and chemical pedagogy tools.

### **Education:**

- **Ph.D. in Computational Chemistry** on Semiclassical molecular dynamics. University of Alcalá, (Spain 2011-2015).
- M.Sc. in Chemistry on Automatic generation of QM/MM models for photoactive proteins. University of Siena, (Italy 2008-2011).

Email:
acuzzio@gmail.com
Mobile:
+1 (650)250-9263
Web:
www.alessiovalentini.com
LinkedIn

### **Python libraries:**

Cython NetworkX Numpy/Scikit Pandas Matplotlib Rdkit/OpenBabel Mkdocs

# Secondary languages:

CUDA C/C++ Fortran React/Javascript

### Daily tools:

Bash VScode JupyterLab Docker CI/CD

#### Misc:

Blender Gimp Inkscape Latex d3.js

### Real life languages:

Italian English Spanish

